so yes reading the supers is um
is very important it's really necessary
because uh as we said many times before
it's been two and a half millennia since
the buddha passed away so
with all the contemporary teachings you
should make a practice
of um of reading the suitors and study
them study them in a sense of
study them in a sense of
read reread investigate the meaning
then go back to the suttas that sort of
inspired you more
and you know
you know
look at different translations look into
pali look at the meaning and the of the
individual politeness and words that are
relevant because um
because um
well it's
there's so much so much stuff outside
so many different instructions views
opinions and
and
especially when you're beginning
the practice
you don't really know what is right or
what is wrong but you can certainly use
your intelligence to discern what is
least likely to be wrong and that is the
suitors so
you don't even know that they are right
i mean if you're a beginner beginner you
wouldn't know that even the the sutas
came from the buddha or they're accurate
or or anything really there's no there's
no way to verify it you can just you
know look at them scholastically
historically and so on but
fundamentally it's just been so long
that you can't really prove it to
disprove it so use your intelligence to
discern what is as i said
what is as i said
um
generally be the the best course of
action with least risk for somebody who's just
with least risk for somebody who's just
starting to practice but even if you're
not just starting to practice
uh again unless you're at least a soda
partner you haven't really understood
the sutures you haven't really
understood where the right view is
which means you should not think
um that you have
they should have enough of suitors and
now you need to do something else or
find out some technique or something to
put it in practice understanding the
suit is the practice understanding the
buddha's word
um is what leads you out of suffering
uh not uh you know not a practice not an
observation not a meditation technique none of that
not a meditation technique none of that
it's it's it's genuinely uh
understanding how to regard your own
experience within yourself
they will result in you being unable to
suffer so that for me you could you should make
so that for me you could you should make
a make a routine
make a practice
not out of a meditation technique but
out of a suit study
then if you get the right view when you
get the right view
when you develop the right view then you
will know what zamad is and you will
know what type of meditation is suitable
for your mind to
increase the wholesomeness of it and
decrease the unwholesomeness and so on
but in the meantime
it is not really optional take a take
into the translation read it
take another translation read it look
into pali don't necessarily confused
studying the meaning of the suttas with
the pali scholarship
pali scholarship
if the mind is inclined towards that
side of things that's fine but still the
context for your scholarship and uh and
learning poly and so on should be
to uh understand the meaning and there
is a risk there
that the more information you get about the
the more information you get about the
term or the word
in general
that information will be confused for
understanding the meaning of it
but that's not the case
because if that were the case pure
scholarship would result in other
hanship and it doesn't necessarily even result
and it doesn't necessarily even result
in the right view more often than not
so
so i mean get into detail if you need so
um
you know dictionaries poly
different translations different
interpretations but all for the sake of
understanding a meaning for yourself
and uh and you can actually apply the
same even you know not just to pali and
the sutra study to pretty much anything
you're trying to understand so your
state of mind or even in your own
language i think i probably said that
before but
like you know
in english if you use the word
consciousness or feeling
or matter
what is it
that you're referring to like do you see
for yourself
that phenomenon that you are designating
in your own speech colloquially when you
say oh i'm conscious of this so what is
that consciousness part
like do you see that in your experience
that you're referring to or is it just
an empty designation or is just an
ambiguous designation
so
is it the term that you have understood
uh the meaning of
so if you say feeling what do you refer
to do you refer to bodily sensations
do you refer to states of mind
are you clear about it
or is just like a
you know
all these colloquial terms are taken for
granted as something they are understood
while in reality they're just used
basically on the surface
and without any any degree of greater
understanding of the meaning behind it
so
because there has to be a phenomenon uh
even when you say feeling i'm feeling
this i'm feeling that or the matter of
this or the consciousness
there has to be a phenomenon that you're
designating there has to be something in
your experience that is standing for
that matter you're talking about
what is it do you see it for yourself
and during there while you're talking
about it
so
from that point of view you don't even
need pali just understand the five
aggregates in your own language
understand what they are here and now
how they're experienced as the enduring
phenomena in your experience as a whole
and yeah your rupa done in regard to
them will be diminishing because the
clarity of the nature is becoming
clearer and and that's the reason why there is
and and that's the reason why there is
no um
the uh
the clarity in regard to the nature of
this phenomenon being developed
it's because uh
the um they're used
in that ambiguous sense
and uh there is people don't make the
effort to go to go against that
to go to go against that
and uh because
again you just kind of have some general
idea of what
consciousness is and you you regard that
as sufficient
and now on top of that idea of
consciousness you try to understand
other ideas of consciousness but even
your own presently enduring
consciousness is not seen for what it is
on account of those ideas
not account of some other
interfering aging that is blocking you
from understanding it no it's your ideas
that make you think you understood it
are preventing you from understanding it
so remove those ideas and what you're
left with is the the nature of
consciousness the nature of the five
aggregates or wherever you direct your
mind the nature of the four noble truths
the nature of suffering what is
suffering as an enduring phenomenon what is this
as an enduring phenomenon what is this
unpleasant feeling
is it always when you felt unpleasantly
did you always suffer or you only only
suffer sometimes on a kind of unpleasant
feeling that's present not always so
then you realize okay so there's more to
it it's not a feeling
in itself by default so what is feeling
then what is that which is being felt
that phenomenon
what is it that you're designating when
you say i feel like this or i feel like
that so
so
it's basically that that's what i'm
pointing at is that direction of the
mind that instead of um taking the
that instead of um taking the
information and designations for granted
uh looks at the meaning behind and is
trying to understand that
um
and whether you you apply that
to your own language and terminology
through your own thinking to the suitors
to pali or whatever it's the same
direction it's the same principle and it
needs to be developed that's a kind of
prerequisite for the right view